Yang Chen

JSPS Research Fellow (PD), Visiting Post-doc (ETH Zurich)

Phone: 81-07039953300 | Email: chenyang@ai.iit.tsukuba.ac.jp

Address: Zurich

Personal website: https://robot-yang.github.io/



Summary

I am a robotics researcher and life-long learner. I obtained Ph. D. degree in human informatics from University of Tsukuba in March 2023 and currently working as a visiting post-doc at ETH Zurich and research fellow (PD) of Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS). My research interests include but are not limited to human augmentation, human-robot interaction, mobile robotics, teleoperation, human sensing, assistive technology, shared control, etc.

Research goal: Use robotics technology to empower humans.

Working experience

ETH Zurich June.2023-Dec. 2023

Visiting post-doc

Lab: SMS Lab & SCAI Lab

Research topic: Shared control for a holonomic wheelchair Hosted by: Prof. Robert Riener & Dr. Diego Paez-Granados

• Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS)

Apr. 2023-Mar. 2024

Research fellow (PD)

Hosted by: Prof. Kenji Suzuki

Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS)

Apr. 2022-Mar. 2023

Research fellow (DC)

• University of Tsukuba Apr. 2020-Nov. 2021

Research Assistant

Education

• Jilin University Sep. 2013-Jun. 2017

Bachelor of Engineering in Mechanical Engineering (Excellent Engineers Training Program, Ministry of Education) Supervised by Prof. DongF. Wang

Bachelor thesis: Explore the Way of Designing the Piezoelectric Dividing Structure to Both Realize the Stress Distributing Evenly and Achieve Largest Output Voltage

University of Tsukuba
 Oct. 2017-Apr. 2018

Research student

• University of Tsukuba Apr. 2018-Mar. 2020

Master of Human Informatics

Master thesis: Torso Control System and Autonomous Docking Support for a Standing Mobility Device

• University of Tsukuba Apr. 2018-Mar. 2023

Ph. D Program in Empowerment Informatics

Doctoral thesis: A Study on Upper-body based Shared Navigation Control for Assistive Mobility Devices

Supervised by Prof. Kenji Suzuki

Internship

• École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL)

Aug. 2019-Oct. 2019

Lab: Learning Algorithm and System Laboratory (LASA)

Research topic: Autonomous docking system for a standing mobility device

Supervised by Prof. Aude Billard

• National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology (AIST)

Aug. 2021-Present

Lab: CNRS-AIST JRL (Joint Robotics Laboratory),

Research topic: Complementary SLAM for Immersive Teleoperation with A Humanoid

Supervised by Prof. Fumio Kanehiro

Main Projects

- Shared control for a holonomic wheelchair

 This work aims to propose a shared control framework for a holonomic wheelchair to improve user's experience.
- Wearable Mobility Device Adapting to User's Natural Posture Changes

 Aug. 2019-Present
 In this work, we aim to realize a novel concept of a personal mobility device design that combines the agile mobility of a wheel type mechanism but does not limit a human's natural stair climbing ability.
- Control interface for hands-free navigation of personal mobility vehicles

 Oct. 2017-Present
 This work aims to explore an intuitive and simple control interface for personal mobility devices that would allow handsfree locomotion.
- Virtual landmark-based control of docking support for assistive mobility devices

 Oct. 2018-Present
 This works proposes an autonomous docking support approach for assistive mobility devices like intelligent wheelchairs
 to assists the user in approaching a rest surface, such as a chair or bed. A stable nonlinear feedback control is constrained
 to field of view (FOV) by transforming the target volume to a virtual landmark pose. The effectiveness is demonstrated
 with a real-time implementation on a standing mobility vehicle Qolo, using embedded RGBD sensing.
- Enhanced Visual Feedback with Decoupled Viewpoint Control in Immersive Humanoid Robot Teleoperation using SLAM

 Aug. 2021-Present

 This work aims to enhance the tele-visualization experience for the operator in humanoid robot teleoperation, we construct a virtual space for decoupled viewpoint control, and we use a prebuilt mesh to complement the real-time point cloud to reduce the visual latency.

Publication

- <u>Y. Chen</u>, D. Paez-Granados, M. Hassan, and K. Suzuki, "Torso-Based Control Interface for Standing Mobility-Assistive Devices", IEEE/ASME Transactions on Mechatronics, 2024. (Under review, preprint, video)
- R. Cisneros-Lim'on, A. Dallard, M. Benallegue, K. Kaneko, H. Kaminaga, P Gergondet, A Tanguy, Rohan P. Singh, L. Sun, Y. Chen, C. Fournier, M. Tsuru, S'elim C. Moussaoui1, G. Lorthioir, Y. Osawa, G. Caron, M. Morisawa, A. Escande, K. Ayusawa, I. Kumagai, M. Ono, K. Shirasaka, S. Wada, H. Wada, F. Kanehiro and A. Kheddar, "A cybernetic avatar system to embody human telepresence for connectivity, exploration and skill transfer" International Journal of Social Robotics, 2023. (Peer-reviewed, link)
- <u>Y. Chen</u>*, T. Kuwahara*, Y. Nishimura[†], K. Suzuki, "WeMo: A Prototype of Wearable Mobility Device Adapting to User's Natural Posture Changes", Sensors, 2023. (**Peer-reviewed**, <u>link</u>)
- R. Cisneros, A. Dallard, M. Benallegue, K. Kaneko, H. Kaminaga, P. Gergondet, A. Tanguy, C. Fournier, Rohan P. Singh, <u>Y. Chen</u>, Sélim C. Moussaoui, G. Lorthioir, Y. Osawa, M. Tsuru, L. Sun, M. Morisawa, G. Caron, F. Kanehiro, A. Kheddar, "Enhancement of Team JANUS' cybernetic avatar system for exploration and skill transfer", *ICRA 2023 Workshop Toward Robot Avatars*. (Peer-reviewed, link)
- Santiago P. Torrendell, <u>Y. Chen</u>, H. Kadone, M. Hassan, K. Suzuki, "Design of a Multi-Degree-of-Freedom Elastic Neck Exoskeleton for Persons with Dropped Head Syndrome", 6th IEEE-RAS International Conference on Soft Robotics (RoboSoft), 2023. (Peer-reviewed, link)
- Y. Chen, L. Sun, M. Benallegue, R. Cisneros-Limón, Rohan P. Singh, K. Kaneko, A. Tanguy, G. Caron, K. Suzuki, A. Kheddar, and F. Kanehiro, "Enhanced Visual Feedback with Decoupled Viewpoint Control in Immersive Humanoid Robot Teleoperation using SLAM," IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids), 2022. (Peer-reviewed, link)
- R. Cisneros, M. Benallegue, K. Kaneko, H. Kaminaga, G. Caron, A. Tanguy, R. Singh, L. Sun, A. Dallard, C. Fournier, M. Tsuru, <u>C. Yang</u>, Y. Osawa, G. Lorthioir, F. Kanehiro, A. Kheddar. "Team JANUS Humanoid Avatar: A cybernetic avatar to embody human telepresence". RSS 2022 Workshop on "Towards Robot Avatars: Perspectives on the ANA Avatar XPRIZE Competition", New York City, U.S.A., 2022. (Peer-reviewed, link)
- D. Paez-Granados, H. Kadone, M. Hassan, Y. Chen, & K. Suzuki, "Personal Mobility With Synchronous Trunk-Knee Passive Exoskeleton: Optimizing Human-Robot Energy Transfer", IEEE/ASME Transactions on Mechatronics, 2021. (**Peer-reviewed, IF** = **5.673**, **link**)
- Y. Chen, D. F. Paez Granados, B. Leme and K. Suzuki, "Virtual Landmark Based Control of Docking Support for Assistive Mobility Devices," in IEEE/ASME Transactions on Mechatronics, doi: 10.1109/TMECH.2021.3081426. (Peer-reviewed, IF = 5.673, link)
- Y. Chen, D. Paez-Granados, H. Kadone and K. Suzuki, "Control Interface for Hands-free Navigation of Standing Mobility Vehicles based on Upper-Body Natural Movements," 2020 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS), 2020, pp. 11322-11329, doi: 10.1109/IROS45743.2020.9340875. (Peerreviewed, link)
- Y. Chen, D. Paez-Granados, and K. Suzuki, "Holistic body machine interface solution for standing mobility vehicle for the lower-body impaired-integrating autonomous docking system-," in The Proceedings of JSME annual Conference on Robotics and Mechatronics (Robomec) 2020. The Japan Society of Mechanical Engineers, 2020, pp. 2P1–D10. (Non-peer-reviewed, link).

- Y. Chen, D. Paez-Granados and K. Suzuki, "Torso Control System with A Sensory Safety Bar for a Standing Mobility Device," 2019 International Symposium on Micro-NanoMechatronics and Human Science (MHS), 2019, pp. 1-5, doi: 10.1109/MHS48134.2019.9249303. (Peer-reviewed, link)
- Y. Liu, <u>Y. Chen</u> et al., "Developing MEMS electric current sensors for end use monitoring of power supply: Part VIII segmentation design and empirical analysis of piezoelectric layers based on cantilever beam structure," 2018 Symposium on Design, Test, Integration & Packaging of MEMS and MOEMS (DTIP), 2018, pp. 1-4, doi: 10.1109/DTIP.2018.8394240. (Peer-reviewed, link)

Presentation at international conference

- Y. Chen, M. Hassan, D. Paez-Granados, Yosuke Eguchi, Mehdi Benallegue, and K. Suzuki, "Torso Control Interface with Compliant Coupling for Assistive Mobility Devices", Humanoids 2022 Workshop on "the Advances in Close Proximity Human-Robot Collaboration", 2022. (Oral, link)
- Y. Chen, L. Sun, M. Benallegue, R. Cisneros-Limón, Rohan P. Singh, K. Kaneko, A. Tanguy, G. Caron, K. Suzuki, A. Kheddar, and F. Kanehiro, "Enhanced Visual Feedback with Decoupled Viewpoint Control in Immersive Humanoid Robot Teleoperation using SLAM," IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids), 2022. (Poster, peer-reviewed)
- <u>Chen, Y.</u>, Paez-Granados, D., Leme, B., and Suzuki, K., "Virtual Landmark Based Control of Docking Support for Assistive Mobility Devices", IEEE/ASME International Conference on Advanced Intelligent Mechatronics, 2021. (**Oral, peer-reviewed**)
- Y. Chen, D. Paez-Granados, H. Kadone, and K. Suzuki, "Control interface for hands-free navigation of standing mobility vehicles based on upper-body natural movements," in 2020 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS). IEEE, 2020. (**Oral, peer-reviewed**)
- Y. Chen, D. Paez-Granados, and K. Suzuki, "Torso Control System with A Sensory Safety Bar for a Standing Mobility Device," in International Symposium on Micro-Nano Mechatronics and Human Science (MHS-2019), MEXT, Ed. Nagoya, Japan: IEEE, 2019. (Oral, peer-reviewed)

Presentation at domestic conference

- Y. Chen, D. Paez-Granados, and K. Suzuki, "Holistic body machine interface solution for standing mobility vehicle for the lower-body impaired—integrating autonomous docking system—," in The Proceedings of JSME Annual Conference on Robotics and Mechatronics (Robomec). (Poster, non-peer-reviewed)
- <u>Chen Yang</u>, Diego Paez-Granados, Kenji Suzuki, "Upper-Body Sensing Based Control System with Docking Support on A Standing Mobility Device", 生体医工学シンポジウム, 予稿・抄録集, 2019, 1A-23. (**Poster, non-peer-reviewed**)

Honors & Awards

- Mathematical Modeling Contest Third Prize
- 1st prize in First Robot Competition of Jilin University
- Finalist (5/80, \$500,000 grant received) in <u>Toyota Mobility Unlimited Challenge</u>

 Apr. 2018-Dec. 2020
 The \$4 million Mobility Unlimited Challenge supports radical improvements in the mobility and independence of people with lower-limb paralysis through smarter assistive technology. We (<u>Team Qolo</u>) developed a mobile exoskeleton on wheels, allowing users to sit or stand with ease.
- JST SPRING Fellowship Qualified Student (Class 1)

Oct. 2021-Mar 2022

Mar. 2017-May 2017

• Finalist of the ANA Avatar XPRIZE international competition: Team Janus

Mar. 2018-Present

Dec. 2015

Skills

- Programming language: Python, MATLAB, C++
- Software tools: Linux, ROS, Unity
- 3D/2D Modelling: CATIA, Solid works, AutoCAD, Fusion 360
- Electronics: EAGLE
- Language: Chinese (native), English (full professional proficiency), Japanese (N2)

Research Grants

• 2019

• Challenge Grant 300,000 Japanese yen

• 2020

• Challenge Grant 300,000 Japanese yen

• 2021

• Challenge Grant 300,000 Japanese yen

- 2022-2024
 - Grant-in-Aid for JSPS Fellows

2300,000 Japanese yen

Scholarship

- 2015~2017
 - University Scholarship (3rd-class), Jilin University
- 2018~2021
 - Special Fellows Scholarship, University of Tsukuba
- 2021~2022
 - JST SPRING Fellowship (1st-class), JST
- 2022~2024
 - JSPS Fellowship (DC2), JSPS

Academic Service (review)

- RAL 2022 [2]
- IROS 2022 [1]
- T-MECH 2022 [1]
- HRI 2023 [1]
- RAL 2023 [1]
- RAL 2024 [1]